Guide to the Henry Onderdonk Papers ARC.045
Brooklyn Historical Society
Henry Onderdonk papers
1729-1895
Brooklyn Historical Society
Onderdonk, Henry
ARC.045
10 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes and 4 flat boxes
Henry Onderdonk (1804-1886) of Queens County, Long Island, New York, was an educator at Union Hall Academy, and an historian and author of many works based on his research among local records. The Onderdonk papers include manuscript versions of Onderdonk's historical works; notes and transcriptions taken by Onderdonk from private journals, church and local government records, and newspapers; correspondence from historians, genealogists and others often conveying information requested by Onderdonk; and scrapbooks of newspaper clippings covering the 1820s to 1868, with some earlier and later dated material. The bulk of the material concerns the geographic area encompassing present day Queens and Nassau counties, though the other two counties on Long Island, Kings and Suffolk, are also represented. The historical manuscripts, notes and extensive correspondence in the collection tend to center around Onderdonk's research into the American Revolution, Quakers, churches, agriculture/animal husbandry, and genealogies, all with a focus on Long Island. Perhaps the most prominent correspondent is James Fenimore Cooper, whose three letters concern Loyalist Oliver de Lancey. Among the many other correspondents are historians George Bancroft, E. F. Ellet, E. B. O'Callaghan, Jeptha Root Simms, and Jared Sparks. The several scrapbooks in the collection, also with a Long Island focus, concern a number of subjects, principally electoral and partisan politics, agriculture, temperance, announcements and public notices for a wide variety of events, such as school openings, church dedications, auctions, cultural talks, etc., crimes and accidents, court proceedings, Civil War recruitments and drafts, and railroad developments, among other matters.
Arrangement
The Onderdonk papers are organized in four series:
Series 1: Historical Manuscripts and Notes
Series 2: Correspondence
Series 3: Miscellaneous
Series 4: Scrapbooks
Biographical / Historical
Henry Onderdonk (1804-1886) was an educator and historian, a collector of Long Island antiquities, and the author of many works based on his findings among local records. Later, he became a founder (1863) and councilor (1868-1886) of the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society), and a contributor to the Society's library and manuscript collections upon their formation.
Henry Onderdonk was born June 11, 1804, at Manhasset, NY, the son of Joseph Onderdonck, a farmer, and Dorothy Monfoort. Henry commonly rendered his name with a "Jr."; it is supposed that he did so to distinguish his name from that of his eminent relative, Henry Ustick Onderdonk (1789-1858), the Protestant Episcopal Bishop of Pennsylvania. Onderdonk graduated from Columbia College in 1827 and received an A.B. degree from Harvard in 1828. He married Maria Hegeman Onderdonk (1801-1875), daughter of George Onderdonk and Sarah Rapalije in 1828, and had two children, Elizabeth (1829-fl. 1909) and Adrian (1831-1888). Henry took up teaching, becoming principal of Union Hall Academy at Jamaica from 1832 to 1865, after which he devoted himself to literary pursuits. He was also a director of the Long Island Bible Society. Onderdonk died at Jamaica on June 22, 1886 and is buried in Monfort Cemetery in Port Washington, NY.
Onderdonk's career in historical and genealogical study may have been inspired by his father's tales as a young witness to the Revolutionary war period on Long Island and in New York City. Joseph Onderdonck, born in 1766, saw his father, Andries, a Deputy Chairman of the Whig Committee, taken prisoner by the British, 21 September 1776. After experiencing many scenes of the British military occupation of Long Island, Joseph was present at the Federal procession in New York (23 July 1788) and at the inauguration of George Washington as President of the U. S. (30 April 1789), and later often saw Washington around town.
Henry Onderdonk's first published works focused on local events during the American Revolution, and relied on eye-witness accounts; these early writings included Documents and letters intended to illustrate the revolutionary incidents of Queens County, N.Y. (1846), The capture and death of Brig. Gen. Nath'l Woodhull: In a series of letters addressed to J. Fenimore Cooper Esq (1848) and Revolutionary incidents of Suffolk and Kings Counties: With an account of the Battle of Long Island and the British prisons and prison-ships at New York (1849). Onderdonk's later works included writings about various Long Island churches, the Society of Friends (Quakers), and agriculture. While Onderdonk became a prolific writer of local and religious histories, he is perhaps most notable as a collector, compiler, and preservationist of official and military papers, diaries, old newspapers, oral histories, and many early records of Long Island towns and churches.
Because so much of Onderdonk's work concerns a geographic area called Queens County, it is helpful to recall that the Queens County of Onderdonk's time differed from that of today. Until 1899, Queens County consisted not only of the present-day county and New York City borough of the same name, but also all of what is now Nassau County. Some Queens County towns (e.g., Jamaica, Flushing) were consolidated into New York City in 1898, while others were not. Those not consolidated (e.g., Hempstead, Oyster Bay) were removed from Queens County in 1899 to form the new Nassau County. Accordingly, all references in this guide, and in the collection, to Queens County can be taken to include Nassau County as well.
(The above was based on a biographical note written in 2005 by Jonathan W. Montgomery. Additional sources: Genealogy of the Onderdonk family in America, edited by Andrew Joseph Onderdonk and Florence Evelyn Pratt Youngs; http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monfort_Cemetery; http://www.nassaucountyny.gov/website/EN/facts_stats_maps/history_of_NC.html.)
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance of all the materials in the Onderdonk papers has not been definitively traced. Nonetheless several of the manuscripts and all the scrapbooks in the collection bear a bookplate indicating that they were presented to the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society) by Onderdonk. There is little doubt that most of the correspondence and other manuscripts also were given by him to BHS. Some of the material was donated by Onderdonk's daughter Elizabeth in 1909; this included much of the material in the Miscellaneous series along with some correspondence and several manuscripts.
Scope and Contents
The Henry Onderdonk papers include manuscript versions of Onderdonk's historical works; notes and transcriptions taken by Onderdonk from various historical sources; correspondence from historians, genealogists and others often conveying information requested by Onderdonk; and scrapbooks of newspaper clippings covering the 1820s to 1868, with some earlier and later dated material. The bulk of the material concerns Queens County, New York, which in Onderdonk's time also included present-day Nassau County. The other two counties on Long Island, Kings and Suffolk, are also represented in the collection, though not to the extent of Queens.
The historical manuscripts and notes in the collection tend to center around the American Revolution, Quakers, churches, agriculture/animal husbandry, and genealogies, all with a focus on Long Island. While some of these manuscripts and notes include Onderdonk's own writings, most consist of his transcriptions and extracts of private journals, church and local government records, and newspapers. The extensive correspondence in the collection centers on these themes as well, and includes much correspondence to Onderdonk from historians, genealogists, and others providing him with information in response to his inquiries in these subject areas. The correspondence includes several notable mid-nineteenth century American historians and provides insight into the conduct of their research and scholarly networks during the first generations of American historical writing. These correspondents include George Bancroft, E. F. Ellet, E. B. O'Callaghan, Jeptha Root Simms, and Jared Sparks, among many others. Perhaps the most prominent correspondent is James Fenimore Cooper; the collection includes three substantive letters from Cooper concerning General Oliver de Lancey, the Loyalist who fought for the British on Long Island during the Revolution.
The several scrapbooks in the collection concern a number of subjects, principally electoral and partisan politics, agriculture, temperance, announcements and public notices for a wide variety of events, such as school openings, church dedications, auctions, cultural talks, etc., crimes and accidents, court proceedings, Civil War recruitments and drafts, and railroad developments, among other matters. References to African-Americans, while not frequent, appear in the scrapbooks in the context of these subjects, as they do in other parts of the collection. The collection also includes various handbills, fliers, advertisements, programs, and other such material, principally for church and school events, especially in connection with Union Hall Academy of Jamaica in Queens County.
Related Materials
At Brooklyn Historical Society:
An 1854 letter from Onderdonk to Alden Spooner transmitting a book for the Atheneum and requesting others from Spooner can be found in the Spooner collection (ARC.098).
Various Onderdonk transcriptions were further transcribed in typescript by BHS librarians over time. These are on the library's shelves and can be found, along with Onderdonk's published works held by BHS, through the on-line catalog, Bobcat. Use keyword "Henry Onderdonk." Also, some of Onderdonk's transcriptions were published by BHS in the quarterly journal it produced at various times in in its history. The inventory of the journals' content is available through the on-line catablog, Emma, found under the heading Journals of Long Island History. Within the inventory, search "Onderdonk." The journals themselves are in the BHS library.
At least one of Onderdonk's manuscripts is held on the BHS library shelves rather than in the manuscript collection. This is Letters on the death of General Woodhull; also, Suffolk and Kings counties in olden times; Early Dutch ministers of Long Island; History of the Dutch church in Queens County (1866), found at call number E207.W8.O53.1866. Generally, the scrapbook is a compilation of Onderdonk's published newspaper articles. The Woodhull clippings are especially interesting as they include a published debate involving Onderdonk, James Fenimore Cooper, and Lorenzo Sabine about Oliver de Lancey; correspondence in the collection from Cooper and Sabine relates to the published articles.
BHS also holds genealogical information about the Onderdonks. See Genealogy of the Onderdonk family in America (CS71.O53.1910). Also see Edna Huntington's transcription of Onderdonk's journal, Diary or dates of marriage and deaths of my family and friends, 1779-1859, which has more substantive entries than the title suggests (CS71.O53.1934).
Outside BHS:
Queens County Library holds some Henry Onderdonk material in two collections: the Union Hall Academy records and the Joseph Onderdonk Skillman correspondence.
The New-York Historical Society holds scrapbooks of Onderdonk's writings.
The Library of Congress holds two Onderdonk items as part of its Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection (MSS 5670).
Marriage records; Birth records; Burial records; Vital statistics records; Long Island, Battle of, New York, N.Y., 1776; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783; Scrapbooks; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |y Civil War, 1861-1865; Flushing (New York, N.Y.); Local elections |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Hempstead (N.Y.); Local elections |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Suffolk County (N.Y.); Kings County (N.Y.); Nassau County (N.Y.); Agriculture |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Queens County (N.Y.); African Americans |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Jamaica (New York, N.Y.); Fourth of July |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Fliers (printed matter); Quakers |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Quakers |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Transcripts; Correspondence; Clippings (information artifacts); North Hempstead (N.Y.: Town); Oyster Bay (N.Y.); Long Island (N.Y.); County courts; Temperance |x Societies, etc.; Crime |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Church announcements; Fourth of July |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Crime |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Railroad companies |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Genealogy; Genealogies; Press and politics; Agriculture |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Hicks, John D. -- Correspondence; Hicks, Benjamin Doughty -- Correspondence; Ellet, E. F. (Elizabeth Fries) -- Correspondence; Frost, Gideon -- Correspondence; Johnson, Jeremiah -- Correspondence; Cooper, James Fenimore -- Correspondence; Bancroft, George -- Correspondence; Latting, John Jordan -- Correspondence; Union Hall Academy (Jamaica, New York, N.Y.); Bowne, J. T. (Jacob Titus) -- Correspondence; Corwin, Edward Tanjore -- Correspondence; Bergen, Teunis G. -- Correspondence; Onderdonk, Henry; Strong, Thomas M. -- Correspondence; Sparks, Jared -- Correspondence; Sabine, Lorenzo -- Correspondence; Hoadly, Charles J. (Charles Jeremy) -- Correspondence; O'Callaghan, E. B. (Edmund Bailey) -- Correspondence; Thompson, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin) -- Correspondence; King, John A. -- Correspondence; Stuart, I. W. (Isaac William) -- Correspondence; Queens County Agricultural Society (N.Y.); De Lancey, Oliver; Simms, Jeptha Root -- Correspondence; Lossing, Benson John -- Correspondence; Jones, William Alfred -- Correspondence
- Series 1: Historical Manuscripts and Notes, 1762-1884; 1.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of Historical Manuscripts and Notes includes Onderdonk's transcriptions, abstracts, and notes from various church and local government records, private journals, and newspapers. The series includes a small number of print versions of Onderdonk's works and of manuscripts of Onderdonk's own writing. Most of the documents in the series concern towns in nineteenth-century Queens County (which included present-day Nassau County), but towns in Suffolk County are also represented. The series also holds material on towns in Kings County, though to a lesser extent than other Long Island locales.
  Many of the documents in the series have a topical focus, with the principal subjects concerning the American Revolution, Quakers (or Friends), and agriculture, including animal husbandry. These documents include transcriptions of Revolutionary-era correspondence to Major John Kissam of the Queens militia and of Quaker John Bowne's journal of imprisonment and account book. Documents concerning "olden times" are more wide-ranging, spanning social issues, commercial ventures, agriculture/farming, crime, church/religion, politics/governance, slavery, etc. Many documents are principally lists of marriages, deaths, baptisms, wills filed with the surrogate's office, tax lists, etc. Some of the manuscripts include an index.
  Many of the notebooks in the series were constructed from previously-used documents, especially correspondence from circa 1870s to the clerk of Queens County, but also advertisements and other printed matter. Onderdonk wrote on the blank reverse sides of these documents, and much of the original content can still be viewed. A substantive example is an account book of fees received in 1866-67 by surrogate William H. Onderdonk.
  Aside from the original artifacts comprising many of the notebooks themselves, there are few original records in the series. Significant exceptions to this are the wampum, bills of credit and paper currency attached to pages of Onderdonk's historical sketch of agriculture. Some of the notebooks include paper slips with signatures; it is not clear whether these are original signatures cut from documents or Onderdonk's tracings of the original signatures.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged roughly by subject. The series opens with Onderdonk's bibliographies of Long Island history and material with a specific topical focus (e.g., Revolutionary War). These materials are followed by those of a more general nature (e.g., lists of marriages and baptisms).
  Folder descriptions referring to printed matter use italics to distinguish the content from manuscript content.
  For manuscript material consisting principally of transcribed records, an approximate date range of the records is included in the folder description. The folder date itself refers to the manuscript date, any dated artifacts comprising the pages of the manuscript, and/or original dated artifacts found in the manuscript.
  - Bibliography of Long Island, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography of Long Island, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bibliography of Long Island, 1866-1874 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Revolutionary Incidents in Queens County - Manuscript and Notes (2 folders), 1846-1884 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Supplement to the Revolutionary Incidents of Suffolk and Kings Counties, 1776-1789, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Revolutionary Incidents at Huntington, 1776-1783, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters Addressed to Major John Kissam of the Queens Militia, 1777-1786, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Worcester Book / Hempstead Notes (including notes on Revolution), 1727-1792, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - John Bowne's Journal of his Imprisonment, 1662-1664; Extracts from Account Book of John and Samuel Bowne, 1649-1701, circa 1871 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - History of Friends in Flushing and New York City, 1658-1819, circa 1872 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - History of Friends on Long Island, 1672-1797, circa 1872 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Friends on Long Island and in New York, circa 1872 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Quakers at Hempstead; Annals of Hempstead, circa 1870 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Genealogy of the Hegeman and Monfort Families, 1580-1859, circa 1860 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    General
    Small clippings from 1885, 1907, and 1961 related to the Hegeman family were tipped into the manuscript.
  - Some Notes for a History of Horse-Breeding and Horse-Racing in Queens County, 1665-1869 (in account book that includes Fees Received by Wm. H. Onderdonk, Surrogate, 1866-1867), 1788, circa 1870 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Farming in Olden Times in Queens County, 1656-1708, circa 1868 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Historical Sketch of Ancient Agriculture, Stock Breeding, and Manufactures in Hempstead, 1762-1790, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Manuscript includes bills of credit, currency, and a string of wampum glued to the reverse side of pages 20 and 21. See the Correspondence series for a letter likely concerning the source of the wampum.
  - Queens County in Olden Times Articles in Long Island Farmer, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - History of Dutch Churches of Queens County, 1773-1876, 1861-1876 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Notes for Historical Sketch on Manhasset and Other Long Island Locales, 1650-1832, circa 1869 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Queens County in Olden Times, 1639-1832, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Long Island in Olden Times - Selected Articles, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Long Island in Olden Times, 1639-1828, circa 1864 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Long Island in Olden Times, 1639-1827, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Indices to Names in Queens and Suffolk Counties in Olden Times, circa 1865 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Extracts from Historical Newspapers, 1737-1770, circa 1824 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - List of Names in the Old Records of Several Towns in Queens County, 1661-1778, circa 1872 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Names in Queens County Records (Quaker and Court Records), 1722-1774, circa 1868 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Monthly, Quarterly, and Yearly Meetings at Flushing, 1663-1703, circa 1865 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jamaica Records, Vols 1 and 2, 1656-1803, circa 1874 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Jamaica Reformed Dutch Church Baptisms, 1702-1823, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Births, Marriages, Deaths of Friends (Long Island), 1630-1821, circa 1871 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Long Island Churches, Ministers, and Baptisms, 1654-1875, circa 1877 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - List of New York Loyalists, 1776; List of New York Police Officers, 1777; Tombstone Inscriptions, Grace Church, Jamaica, 1742-1863; Marriages, Births, and Baptisms, Presbyterian Church, Jamaica, 1679-1848, 1846, 1875-1877 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Church Records of Newtown, Jamaica, Success, Manhasset, Oyster Bay - Consistory Notes, Building Sketches, Baptisms, Marriages, Funerals, 1710-1859, 1818, 1859 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Indexes to Wills in Surrogate's Office, Queens County and Hempstead, 1665-1786, 1867 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lists from Long Island Towns - Tax Lists, Names from Town Records, Student Names, Supervisor's Book Extracts, Patentees, 1653-1844, circa 1850 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lists from Hempstead and Cow Neck Records, 1645-1811; Correspondence from Maria to Catherine Onderdonk, 1802-1811, 1852 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Baptisms and Marriages in the Episcopal Church, Hempstead, 1725-1845, circa 1874 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Marriages and Baptisms by Rev. Joshua Hart of Huntington and Hempstead, 1772-1826, circa 1874 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Baptisms and Marriages in the Reformed Dutch Churches, Kings County, 1660-1775, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lists of Names in Wills and Other Records, 1680-1756, circa 1868 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1835-1885; 1 Linear Feet
  Other Finding Aids
  A supplemental finding aid that provides a more detailed summary of the correspondence in series 2.1 is included with the collection at the beginning of the series. The supplemental finding aid is also available on the Emma catablog.
  The Correspondence series includes the extensive correspondence sent to Onderdonk by historians, genealogists, librarians, and others. This correspondence both requested information of Onderdonk and provided information at his request. The mutual support between Onderdonk and his correspondents in their historical research endeavors is apparent throughout the series.
  As described in the Arrangement Note, the series has four sets of correspondence. These sets are more a reflection of Onderdonk's filing systems, Brooklyn Historical Society's past processing practices, and the varied sources of the correspondence than of any substantial difference in content or chronology. Accordingly, the general themes of the correspondence are consistent across the sets, and many of the correspondents are found in more than one set. Nonetheless, each set has its own strengths: